Guide to the Neil Thomas Proto papers, 1968-2006 MS2275.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Neil Thomas Proto papers
1968-2006
1968-1973
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Proto, Neil Thomas
MS2275.UA
3.75 Linear Feet 1 slim document box, 2 flat boxes, 1 map folder
Neil Thomas Proto is an attorney, writer, and professor based in Washington, D.C. He earned his MA in International Affairs in 1969, and his JD in 1972, at the George Washington University. As a law student at the George Washington University, Proto served as a resident director for two residence halls on campus: Welling Hall and Crawford Hall. Mr. Proto has practiced law for thirty years, and he is currently counsel in the Washington, D.C. firm of Schnader Harrison Segal and Lewis. Since 1990, Mr. Proto has served as an Adjunct Professor at the Georgetown University's Public Policy Institute, and he is the author of the book To A High Court: The Tumult and Choices that Led to United States of America v. SCRAP. The Neil Thomas Proto papers consist of materials that document Proto's time as a residence hall director at GW. The collection dates from 1968 to 2006, with the bulk of the material dating between 1968 and 1972. It includes correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, notes, photographs, newspapers, memorabilia, posters, articles, and the original metal sign from Welling Hall. Most of the material pertains to the political unrest among students at GW, and throughout the country, during the late 1960s and early 1970s.
Material is in good condition. Newspapers ae brittle, and the photographs are in acidic matting.
Biographical / Historical
Neil Thomas Proto is an attorney, writer, and professor based in Washington, D.C. He earned his MA in International Affairs in 1969, and his JD in 1972, at the George Washington University. As a law student at the George Washington University, Proto served as a resident director for two residence halls on campus: Welling Hall and Crawford Hall. The basement game room in Crawford Hall was named in Proto's honor in 1973. Also during this time, Proto was chair of the organization Students Challenging Regulatory Agency Procedures (SCRAP), which fought for compliance by the nation's railroads and the Interstate Commerce Commission with the National Environmental Policy Act. The efforts of SCRAP resulted in the first test in the United States Supreme Court of the National Environmental Policy Act.
Mr. Proto has practiced law for thirty years as an appellate attorney with the United States Department of Justice (Environment and Natural Resources Division, 1972 to 1979), and in private practice. He is currently counsel in the Washington, D.C. firm of Schnader Harrison Segal and Lewis.
In 1988, Mr. Proto was a Visiting Lecturer at Yale University where he taught the history and law of commercial nuclear power. Since 1990, Mr. Proto has served as an Adjunct Professor at the Georgetown University's Public Policy Institute, focusing on environmental values, energy choices, and urban policy. He is the author of numerous articles, and lectures frequently. In 2006, his book about his experiences as a member of SCRAP – To A High Court: The Tumult and Choices that Led to United States of America v. SCRAP – was published by Hamilton Books.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Neil Thomas Proto, 08/05/2009 (2009.044)
Arrangement
Organized into four series: Welling Hall and Crawford Hall, Newspapers, Memorabilia and Posters, and To A Hight Court.
Scope and Contents
The Neil Thomas Proto papers consist of materials that document Proto's work as a director for two residence halls on the George Washington University campus between 1970 and 1972, as well as the political unrest among students at GW and throughout the country during this time period. The collection dates from 1968 to 2006, with the bulk of the material dating between 1968 and 1972. It includes correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, notes, photographs, newspapers, memorabilia, posters, articles, and the original metal sign from Welling Hall.
Dormitory life; Resident assistants (Dormitories) -- United States.; Dormitories -- United States.; Dormitories; Demonstrations; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- United States; Protest movements; Political activists; Students -- Political activity; Student movements; George Washington University -- Students; College students -- America -- Political activity; George Washington University--History; George Washington University. Welling Hall; George Washington University; Proto, Neil Thomas; George Washington University. Crawford Hall
- Welling Hall and Crawford Hall, 05/22/1969-1973 and undated; 1969-1971; Series 1; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 slim document box, 2 flat box boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material pertaining to Neil Thomas Proto's work as a resident director for Welling Hall and Crawford Hall, between 1970 and 1972. The series includes correspondence, memos, minutes, reports, and notes related to the management of each resident hall. Of particular interest are materials regarding demonstrations on the GW campus, student rights, and emerging university policies for handling protests and campus unrest. This series also contains photographs of the dedication of the Neil T. Proto Room in Crawford Hall, and the original metal sign from Welling Hall.
  - Correspondence, Memos, Minutes, Reports, and Notes, 05/22/1969-10/17/1971; 1969-1971; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs--Neil T. Proto Room dedication, Crawford Hall, 1973; Series 1 (Flat box 1)
  - Welling Hall sign, undated; Series 1 (Flat box 2)
- Newspapers, 11/01/1968-05/04/1971; 1968-1971; Series 2; 0.25 Linear Feet 2 folders
  This series contains newspapers collected by Neil Thomas Proto that include articles about student demonstrations on the George Washington University campus and throughout the city, the demolition of Welling Hall, and the political and cultural views of young people in Washington, D.C. from 1968 to 1971. The series includes issues of GW's student newspaper, The Hatchet, and issues of the Washington Free Press.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by newspaper title, then chronologically.
  - Hatchet, 11/08/1968-05/04/1971; 1968-1971; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Washington Free Press, 03/27/1968-11/1/1968; 1968; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Memorabilia and Posters, circa 1968-1970; 1968-1970; Series 3; 2 Linear Feet 1 map folder, 1 flat box, 1 folder (Map-folder 1)
  This series contains memorabilia and posters collected by Neil Thomas Proto that reflect the political atmosphere of the United States between 1968 and 1970. Materials include Robert Kennedy election campaign bumper stickers and brochure, a button, and posters related to the Vietnam War and to student demonstrations and political events held on the George Washington University campus.
  Arranged by format.
  - Memorabilia, circa 1968-1970; 1968-1970; Series 3
    - Button: "Stop the War Machine", undated; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 1)
    - Robert Kennedy election campaign brochure, circa 1968; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 2)
    - Robert Kennedy election campaign bumper stickers (2), circa 1968; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 3)
  - Posters, circa 1968-1970; 1968-1970; Series 3
    - Vietnam: The Movie, circa 1968; Series 3 (Map-folder 1)
    - Elect Yourself in the Streets! Strike!, circa 1970; Series 3 (Flat box 1)
- To A High Court, 2006; Series 4; 0.25 Linear Feet 1 folder
  This series contains material related to the pubication of Neil Thomas Proto's book, "To A High Court: The Tumult and Choices that Led to United States of America v. SCRAP," published in 2006 by Hamilton Books. Materials include articles and reviews of the book, and a glossy reproduction of the book's cover.
  Separated Materials
  A signed copy of Neil Thomas Proto's book, "To A High Court: The Tumult and Choices that Led to United States of America v. SCRAP," was donated with this collection. It has been cataloged and is located in the Special Collections Research Center. The catalog record includes the phrase "Gift of Neil Thomas Proto."
  - Book reviews and cover proof, 2006; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Nuclear safety records, 1980-2009; Series 5; Proto, Neil Thomas; 1 Linear Feet
  Papers and photographs from the President's Nuclear Safety Oversight Committee, articles written by Proto, and syllabi taught by Proto all having to do with nuclear safety.
  - Bruce Babbitt and Three Mile Island newspaper articles, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Course syllabi, 1988-2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    These courses were taught by Proto at Yale (1988-1989) and Georgetown (1990, 1992, 2009).
  - Newspaper articles, 1981-2009 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book proposal and notes on nuclear power, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Proposed court submissions, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    These were prepared for Babbitt but never submitted.
  - International Atomic Energy Conference, Stockholm, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Offer letter, Nuclear Safety Oversight Committee, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Nuclear Safety Oversight Committee (NSOC), 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Nuclear power plant construction, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Pacific Gas and Electric vs. State Energy Resources
  - Vol. 1: Committee purpose and composition (NSOC), 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Vol. 2: Administrative matters and memorandum of understanding (NSOC), 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Vol. 3: Committee reports (NSOC), 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Vol. 4: Memoranda on substance and procedure (NSOC), 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Vol. 5: Personal and NSOC correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - NSOC correspondence and reports, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)